Contact

Lisbon +351964782989 (Mobile) catarina.ramalho@groundforc e.pt

www.linkedin.com/in/ catarinaramalho (LinkedIn) www.groundforce.pt/ (Company) www.pessoas2020.pt/ pessoas2020.html (Other)

Top Skills

Team Management
Negotiation
Organizational Behavior

Languages

French (Full Professional)
Spanish (Elementary)
English (Full Professional)

Honors-Awards

Speaker

Speaker

Prize winning Photographer

Speaker

Speaker

Publications

Boas práticas - Groundforce Portugal

Prize Winning at ASCA Photo Contest

Caderno de Comunicação Interna Testemunho de Catarina Ramalho

Catarina Ramalho

Communications| Groundforce Portugal Lisbon Area, Portugal

Summary

Implementing an Sharepoint Online Intranet, as a one stop shop to communication and employee support needs.

Building Internal and External Comms as a full proof provider to all stakeholders of the organization (int.) and to the organization towards the market, the field and the business (ext.), with special concern on the organization reputation in a very fast paced growing civil and commercial aviation.

Previously, on HR scope

Headed Internal Comms Strategy;

Designed Internal Comms Policies;

Created and managed Internal Comms means;

Reviewed Internal Comms Channels and Managed; Social Media, such as Facebook and a Site Blog;

Managed Internal Comms Programs;

Relevant

Implemented a Change Program;

Managed Organizational Development and IC, wich included:

- 1) HR Programs;
- 2) Performance Appraisal scorecard Task to Skill, Skill to Task and Skill to Goals:
- 3) Implementation an HR Management System within an SaaS Solution:
- 4) New Skills based Approach Model for HR Management;
- 5)Responded to 3 APCER ISO 9001:2000 Audits on behalf of HR;
- 6) Responded to ISAGO Audit (Industry Procedures Compliance).

Managed of DGERT and IATA Accreditation of Groundforce Portugal;

Created and Coordinated Groundforce Academy;

Managed Prime - European Cofinanced Program for Training 2007-2009;

Managed RVCC (Skills and life experience conversion and certification by IEFP and Vocational Training);

Coordinated International Training Projects in African Market; Implemented an E-learning and Training Management System-SUMTOTAL- partner ALTRAN CIS;

Implemented Induction Courses;

Coordinated the first Skills based Approach Model implementation in Groundforce Portugal;

Created an E-learning based Integration/Induction course; Created, Managed and Implemented of the first Language Skills Proficiency Evaluation Model for Recruitment and Selection; Lead E-tutoring;

Was E-coordinator.

Experience

Groundforce Portugal
15 years 8 months

Communication - Internal, External and Corporate February 2019 - Present (1 year 5 months) Lisboa

Head of Internal Communications July 2014 - February 2019 (4 years 8 months)

Responsible for defining and implementing Internal Communication Policies, Strategies and Means/Programs

Organizational Development and Internal Communication Manager July 2014 - July 2015 (1 year 1 month)

Responsible for the definition and implementation of development and internal communication policies.

Responsible for the implementation of HR Projects and Internal Programs. Responsible for the implementation and management of a Skills and Goals based performance appraisal model and process.

Senior Human Capital Specialist June 2013 - July 2014 (1 year 2 months) Responsible for implementing, controlling and reporting Performance Appraisal – 2300 employees

Project Manager

Human Resources Business Partner (HRBP) February 2013 - July 2013 (6 months)

Lisbon Area, Portugal

Responsible for managing and interfacing internal clients needs concerning all HR processes (R&S, Career Plan, Training, Appraisal based on a Skills Model (main process)

Key user SAP RH

Training and Development Coordinator November 2004 - February 2013 (8 years 4 months)

Relevant Projects

Responsible for setting and implementing Training Policies, representing the Organization among stakeholders, clients and during Audits, coordinating the training team (at 2005 managed the Administrative Support) plus 120 trainers, reporting back to Human resources Director training results, challenges and action plan. Assessing training needs and elaborating Training and Development Plan. Responsible for Project Management (from coaching and change programs, to the Accreditation of Groundforce as a Training Entity, to the Certification of all Courses by INAC, to the Certification of Groundforce as a IATA Training School.) Created Groundforce Academy (Training Centre for Commercial purposes)

PGA-Portugália Airlines
Passenger Service Officer
April 2000 - November 2004 (4 years 8 months)

Responsible for Check-in, Boarding and Baggage Management of Portugália Customers.

Escola Secundária de José Gomes Ferreira English Second Language Teacher February 1999 - September 1999 (8 months) Benfica

English Teacher
President of 11th Grade Council
Class Director
Parents Association Manager

Page 3 of 4

TMN-Telecomunicações Móveis Nacionais, SA Customer Service Officer February 1995 - July 1998 (3 years 6 months) Lisbon Area, Portugal

Worked on TMN Call Centre and after a year was invited to manage Customer Relations on Service irregularities

Education

Escola de Gestão e Negócios - EG&N - UAL Master of Business Administration (MBA), Human Resources Management · (2011 - 2012)

Universidade Europeia
Post-grad., Human Resources - Training Management and
Evaluation · (2007 - 2008)

ISLA - LISBOA

Jurisdictional and Technical Translation, Translation and
Linguistics · (1994 - 1998)